<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ruby | Thoughts of Geoff]]></title>
  <link href="http://geopet.github.com/blog/categories/ruby/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geopet.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-07-28T00:12:47-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://geopet.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geoff Petrie]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[g.petrie@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fixing a Slow Localhost Webrick Server]]></title>
    <link href="http://geopet.github.com/blog/2013/01/30/fixing-a-slow-localhost-webrick-server/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-30T23:16:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://geopet.github.com/blog/2013/01/30/fixing-a-slow-localhost-webrick-server</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the longest time I could not get Webrick to work for me. It would boot up with <code>rails s</code> but would take several seconds for even the default landing page of a rails app to load. It was terrible.</p>

<p>I resorted to using <a href="http://code.macournoyer.com/thin/">Thin</a> as my default browser by making sure it was in all my Gem files, but I still wanted to figure out why Webrick simply wouldn&rsquo;t work for me. (Truth is, Thin is a better web server, but I still wanted to get Webrick to work for me.)</p>

<p>Searching for &ldquo;webrick slow&rdquo; brought up a possible solution via <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/3465134/887078">Stack Overflow</a>. Basically you change the <code>:DoNotReverseLookup</code> symbol in your global Webrick config from <code>nil</code> to <code>true</code>.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re on OS X Lion you&rsquo;ll find the Webrick configuration here:</p>

<p><code>~/.rvm/rubies/ruby-1.9.3-p362/lib/ruby/1.9.1/webrick/config.rb</code></p>

<p>I found the <code>:DoNotReverseLookup</code> configuration on line 36.</p>

<p>Once I made the change Webrick was screaming fast. I&rsquo;m pretty happy about it.</p>

<p>I still haven&rsquo;t found the definitive reason why this problem is occurring, but at least this change appears to fix things for me.</p>

<hr />

<p>Please note, depending on the version of Ruby you&rsquo;re running <code>ruby-1.9.3-p362</code> could be something different. Just as long as you&rsquo;re changing the <code>confg.rb</code> file in the <code>webrick/</code> directory, you should be fine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Some Thoughts on Ego]]></title>
    <link href="http://geopet.github.com/blog/2013/01/18/thoughts-on-ego/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-18T10:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://geopet.github.com/blog/2013/01/18/thoughts-on-ego</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To categorically define <em>Ego</em> is out of the scope of this writing. In order to make things easier on myself, and hopefully you, I will attempt to elucidate my meaning through example. But so that we&rsquo;re all starting on the same foot, when I say ego I am referring to the informal and negative connotation of the word.</p>

<p>Why am I talking about ego?</p>

<p>For months now I have been trying to write about my journey as a newbie in the Ruby programming language. I have more than half a dozen starts to what should be a simple short piece of writing. All I wanted to do was provide some preamble so that I could then post the video I used as an entry into the <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/ruby-nuby-project/">Ruby Nuby</a> contest that the <a href="http://rubyrogues.com/">Ruby Rogues</a> podcast put together in October of last year. For some reason every time I attempted to write this article it came out feeling wrong. I&rsquo;m going to try a different take on this subject now.</p>

<p>Several months ago I decided that I needed to broaden my professional horizons. I had been singularly focused on a few programming languages for far too long. I knew I needed to break out of that sedentary place and that there was a fundamental element I was missing. The problem: I didn&rsquo;t know what that element was.</p>

<p>Now I say that several months ago I decided to do something, but the reality is that I have known for years that I could be doing more. <em>This</em> is where ego comes into play.</p>

<p>Ego may be the <em>single biggest impediment to improvement</em>.</p>

<p>Ego prevents us from asking questions. It prevents us from seeking out help. It stops us from acting in an empathetic way. Ego encourages us to be know-it-alls.</p>

<p>The astounding thing about ego is how difficult it is to counteract it. If you call someone out on their ego, what is driving that? There is likely a healthy dose of ego fueling the accusation that someone is filled with hubris. &ldquo;This person is interfering with my greatness, I need to tell them to drop their ego!&rdquo; At least that&rsquo;s what I&rsquo;ve tended to hear when someone has talked about another&rsquo;s ego with me.</p>

<p>But for me, I believe ego has significantly impaired my ability to level up or move forward. I never wanted to accept that I was the least informed, or educated, person in the room. Often times I was being paid to be the most knowledgable person only to realize that I was maybe just slightly more experienced in the subject. Often I was either on even footing or worse! In these situations it wasn&rsquo;t unusual if I found personal security in grabbing my ego tight and running with it. An opportunity for learning? I think not! I would have been more comfortable either attempting to look contemplative, while really just being confused, or, even worse, I would have attempted to derail conversations to a place where I was more familiar.</p>

<p>Was this always the case for me? No. Of course not. But in hindsight it happen more than it should have.</p>

<p>So why am I writing about this?</p>

<p>Ultimately breaking the ego chain was what I needed to write about when I have been trying to talk about starting fresh with Ruby. Yes, embracing newbiness requires a dismissal of ego. But the direction doesn&rsquo;t go newbie to ego. It is the other way around! <em>Ego must go before</em> you can consider being a newbie of anything.</p>

<p>I wish I could say that dumping your ego was easy and that it felt good. Sometimes it does. It certainly depends on the people around you. Having a supportive group does make things simpler.</p>

<p>As a programmer it is tough to dismiss the ego outright. We pride ourselves on reviewing someone&rsquo;s code and finding a bug, or figuring out a more elegant way to write the same method or class. Our ego is what drives us to solve problems! If I didn&rsquo;t think I couldn&rsquo;t do something I hadn&rsquo;t done before I would never have made it in this profession at all. This is a time that ego is a benefit. Ego that pushes us, that drives us to become more than we are, that&rsquo;s something we can embrace. Looking at it in this sense, it isn&rsquo;t incorrect to say that ego is what is driving me to dismiss my ego now. How odd!</p>

<p>So in an effort to move past my typical embarrassment of asking questions that clearly show I don&rsquo;t understand a subject with any sort of depth, or to try something, with varying degrees of success, just so that I can work on that particular skill, I am making a concerted effort to dismiss my ego. I made the video I&rsquo;m embedding below with this in mind as well.</p>

<p>I want to continue to live a fulfilling life. In order for me to do that I need to know that I won&rsquo;t allow something as insignificant as my ego get in the way of asking a question that could lead to a path of new experiences.</p>

<p>At the end of the day this is all about being a happier person.</p>

<p>Thanks for reading.</p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the video that I&rsquo;ve been wanting to post here for months:</p>

<!-- more -->




<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/8enQ96-xOOw?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>As a side note, I&rsquo;ll be a guest on the Ruby Rogues next week and the show will air probably at the end of the month.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
