<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: dns | Thoughts of Geoff]]></title>
  <link href="http://geopet.github.io/blog/categories/dns/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geopet.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-30T12:39:40-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://geopet.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geoff Petrie]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[g.petrie@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adding a CNAME to your Octopress Blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://geopet.github.io/blog/2012/08/22/adding-a-cname-to-your-octopress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-22T16:42:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://geopet.github.io/blog/2012/08/22/adding-a-cname-to-your-octopress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This option isn&rsquo;t terribly well explained in the <a href="http://octopress.org/docs/deploying/github/">Octopress documentation</a>, and slightly confusing within the <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/setting-up-a-custom-domain-with-pages">Github</a>.</p>

<p>So that I could get <em>blog.geoffpetrie.com</em> to work as my url to my Octopress blog hosted by Github at <em>geopet.github.com</em>, I needed to go to my current hosting service. In my case this is currently <a href="http://www.dreamhost.com/r.cgi?1197623">Dreamhost</a>.</p>

<p>Since I wasn&rsquo;t changing my top-level domain (TLD), I wanted to keep <em>geoffpetrie.com</em> pointed at my hosting service, I wanted to add a subdomain, i.e., <em>blog</em> to my domain name server (DNS) run by Dreamhost.</p>

<p>I went into the DNS configuration in the Dreamhost cpanel and added <em>blog</em> as the <strong>name/record</strong>, <em>CNAME</em> as the <strong>type</strong> and <em>geopet.github.com</em> as the <strong>value</strong>.</p>

<p>This is the first step, and once the DNS is refreshed your new subdomain (in my case <em>blog.geoffpetrie.com</em>) will start pointing to a Github 404.</p>

<p>The next step is to add the CNAME to your Octopress <em>master</em> branch. This is surprisingly simple, but not completely intuitive. In the top level of the <em>source</em> branch, you want to use the command:</p>

<p><code>echo 'blog.geoffpetrie.com' &gt;&gt; source/CNAME</code></p>

<p>Of course you&rsquo;re going to use your own subdomain instead of <em>blog.geoffpetrie.com</em>. This command will create the CNAME file in your source directory with the url that you want to direct people to.</p>

<p>After this all that&rsquo;s needed is <code>rake generate</code> and <code>rake deploy</code>. (You may as well commit to your source branch after this.)</p>

<p>Wait a couple of minutes for things to work their way through DNS and Github&rsquo;s world and you&rsquo;ll be looking at your Octopress blog on your own domain.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
