<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: git | Thoughts of Geoff]]></title>
  <link href="http://geopet.github.com/blog/categories/git/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://geopet.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-14T20:40:45-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://geopet.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Geoff Petrie]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[g.petrie@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git Tip: Use Prune to Update Local Repo Branches]]></title>
    <link href="http://geopet.github.com/blog/2012/09/04/some-quick-git-tips/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-04T21:46:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://geopet.github.com/blog/2012/09/04/some-quick-git-tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/git-prune.jpg" title="[pruning the stale branches]" ></p>

<p>I have multiple places where I work and I use <a href="http://git-scm.com/">Git</a> to support that. The general Git workflow I've adopted is similar to the one <a href="http://scottchacon.com/2011/08/31/github-flow.html">Scott Chacon describes</a>.</p>

<p>In Scott's post he explains that anything in <code>master</code> is deployable, and any time you want to work on something you branch from <code>master</code> with something descriptively named. This is what I want to talk about now.</p>

<p>I use this process of branching to keep my changes manageable. By naming my branches descriptively I know that if I'm building a new user profiling tool, and changing the css of a navigational piece and updating a SQL query in the same branch, then the commit isn't going to be terribly clean. Plus, now the branch has no meaning to me when I get feedback from a tester. This branch would make even less sense if I had someone else coding with me.</p>

<p>To keep branches meaningful I make a lot of branches off of <code>master</code>. I've come to the standard practice of pushing pretty much <em>any</em> branch I'm working on, no matter how minor, to the remote. This makes it simple to <code>fetch</code> and <code>merge</code> on my dev server instance instead of scp'ing the work I've done to the server. The process is just feels a little crisper.</p>

<p>After the testers have given the thumbs up on the work and I do my final code review, I merge the branch to master, push it out to production and delete that feature/bugfix branch. All-in-all it is a generally good system.</p>

<p>But what inevitably happens is the dev server has a bunch of branches that are no longer useful and don't have a remote counterpart to them. It gets to be a bit of a mess when you run <code>git branch</code> and see a dozen old branches sitting there.</p>

<p>To fix this issue I found a great, quick command:</p>

<p><code>git remote prune origin</code></p>

<p>Where <code>origin</code> is the name of the remote.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kernel.org/pub/software/scm/git/docs/git-remote.html">From the manual</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p><strong>prune</strong></p>

<p><code>git remote prune [-n | --dry-run] &lt;name&gt;</code></p>

<p>Deletes all stale remote-tracking branches under <code>&lt;name&gt;</code>. These stale branches have already been removed from the remote repository referenced by <code>&lt;name&gt;</code>, but are still locally available in <code>"remotes/&lt;name&gt;"</code>.</p>

<p>With <code>--dry-run</code> option, report what branches will be pruned, but do not actually prune them.</p></blockquote>

<p><code>prune</code> is one of those commands that you may not use very often, but it is nice to know it's there when you need it.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Endnote:</strong></p>

<p>I found this particular <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/a/3994587/887078">Stack Overflow</a> answer useful when I was looking for information on how to handle dead remote branches.</p>

<p><em>Image "Four volunteers prune some plants that were growing over the trail." from <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/presidiosf/6209563606/">United States Government Work</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
